<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practise of the diuell The auncient poisoned practises of the diuell, in his papistes, against the true professors of Gods holy worde, in these our latter daye. Newlie set forth by L. Ramsey.</title>
            <author>Ramsay, Laurence.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10387)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1555:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practise of the diuell The auncient poisoned practises of the diuell, in his papistes, against the true professors of Gods holy worde, in these our latter daye. Newlie set forth by L. Ramsey.</title>
                  <author>Ramsay, Laurence.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Charlewood] for Timothie Rider[, and are to be solde at the lyttle north doore of Paules Church, at the signe of the blacke Boy, by Henrie Kyrkham],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1577?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer and suggested publication date from STC; bookseller from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-C4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:1"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>minated, and him ſelfe decyphered, by the infallyble woorde of God: he nowe (I ſaye) doubles &amp; tryples his inuentions, (as by the ſequell ſhall appeare) twentie tymes tenne folde, to ſubuert and ouerthrowe the true profeſſours of the ſame VVherefore, as in a myrrour, I delyuer this vnto thee, (gentle and loouing Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) manifeſting by this my emulation, moſt of his leger demaynes, againſt God, and our lawfull Kings and Gouernors. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. Ramſey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="body">
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Practiſe of the <hi>Diuell.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Sathan moſt curſed, and childe of perdition,</l>
               <l>Enuy hate and malice, the tyme that is preſent:</l>
               <l>Spytefully complayning, in euery condition,</l>
               <l>Againſt all the world, and all States reſident:</l>
               <l>For putting downe the Pope, my Vicar ſuperintendent,</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> thou bringeſt me in a rage,</l>
               <l>By Preaching true Doctrine, in this thy latter age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But ſéeing that from Heauen, for pride I was caſt,</l>
               <l>Downe into the Helles, in paines perpetuall:</l>
               <l>Aſſure then your ſelues, as long as tyme ſhall laſt,</l>
               <l>Like a roring Lyon, aun Tiger tyrannycall:</l>
               <l>I wyll poyſon your hearts, with ſectes diabolicall,</l>
               <l>With Atheiſts, with Papiſts, with Epicures and Scribes,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Beniamyne,</hi> were horror to the Tribes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I will rayſe vp Sedicion, Luſt and ſelfe Loue,</l>
               <l>Wylfulneſſe and Ignoraunce, and carnall affection:</l>
               <l>That God and all Veritie, I will ſéeke to reproue,</l>
               <l>Reuerting their mindes, to diueliſh ſubiection:</l>
               <l>By ſlaundering and lying, to bréede ſuch infection,</l>
               <l>That all honeſt meaning, both of young and olde,</l>
               <l>Shall cleane be peruerted, and voide of all holde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Anabaptiſts and Arrians, ſhall euery where aſſociate,</l>
               <l>Pelagians and Libertines, in lyke ſhall beare a ſway:</l>
               <l>Vſurers and diſſemblers, by cluſters ſhall accumulate,</l>
               <l>That none ſhall truſt other, afore the latter day:</l>
               <l>Treaſon, theft, and murder, ſhall one an other ſlay.</l>
               <l>By Magick and Witchery, I mynde you ſo to trouble,</l>
               <l>That one ſinne afore, ſhall nowe be ten double.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Paraſites and Flatterers, I wyll make ſo to abound,</l>
               <l>That Trueth ſhalbe defaced, and ſtand aloofe behinde:</l>
               <l>Auarice and Couetouſneſſe, ſhall compaſſe euerie ground,</l>
               <l>That fewe ſhall haue credite, freendſhip to finde,</l>
               <l>Wauerers and Neuters ſhall houer in the winde,</l>
               <l>That Sycophants and brablers, preheminence ſhall haue,</l>
               <l>To predicate and iudicate, before the wyſe and graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Hypocriſie, I knowe my Childe to be aſſured,</l>
               <l>To lyue in all Ages, he hath Wil ſufficient:</l>
               <l>In all kindes of Religion, he is well inured,</l>
               <l>A Doctor in all Artes, to propone an argument:</l>
               <l>Square Cappe and Typpet, the fellowe ſhalbe decent,</l>
               <l>To créepe in among them, hee practiſes to endeuer,</l>
               <l>That I the Diuell his father, may extoll him for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Blaſphemy and Periurie, ſhalbe mates for the rout,</l>
               <l>Flatterie and lying, ſhalbe counted great curteſie:</l>
               <l>With Whordome, I wyll infect the world throughout,</l>
               <l>And that ſhalbe Loue, cloked with great honeſtie,</l>
               <l>Dronkenneſſe &amp; Gluttony, ſhalbe counted great temperancy.</l>
               <l>Couetouſneſſe Wiſdome, Wantonneſſe but Youth,</l>
               <l>Theſe are my practiſes, to blot or dym the Trueth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Infamie and ſlaunder, ſhall runne from place to place,</l>
               <l>Againſt Gods Preachers, or profeſſors of the ſame:</l>
               <l>Terming them Puritans, if ought they haue of Grace,</l>
               <l>Exclayming of theyr lyberties, to hinder theyr good name:</l>
               <l>All that euer is right, I wyll bring out of frame.</l>
               <l>For the malice I beare, to <hi>England</hi> at this ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>I wyll ſtyrre vp vnſpeakable, diuers kindes of Treaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ By Magicke and Sorcerie, ſuch practiſe I wyll worke,</l>
               <l>Reſpecting no degrée, if of God he doo ſmell:</l>
               <l>More cruell then the <hi>Tiger,</hi> more diuelliſhe then the <hi>Turke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More madder then <hi>Saule,</hi> more vyle then <hi>Iezabell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More ſtubborne then <hi>Pharao,</hi> more falſe then <hi>Achytophell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More traytor then <hi>Iudas,</hi> more vnnaturall then <hi>Caine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More villaine then <hi>Abſalon,</hi> which by <hi>Ioab</hi> was ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ More Tyraunt then <hi>Antyochus,</hi> or any of his kinde,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Herodeor Nero,</hi> that tyraunt moſt odious:</l>
               <l>With <hi>Phalaris</hi> and <hi>Domitian,</hi> with thouſands I could finde,</l>
               <l>That to God in this world, haue bene moſt opprobrious:</l>
               <l>But yet in reſpect of my minde malicious,</l>
               <l>They are all but counterfeyts, to that which I intende,</l>
               <l>For the ſpyte that I beare, to the world in th'ende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Lyke a roring Lyon, I rampe, ſtampe, and ſtare,</l>
               <l>Watching iuſt howre, my praye to obtayne:</l>
               <l>Aryſe Infidelytie, voyde of all care,</l>
               <l>Aryſe Hypocriſie, thy Father to maintayne:</l>
               <l>Aryſe Suſpicion, and all Ceremonies vayne,</l>
               <l>Aryſe vp ranke hereſies, againſt God and his Chriſt,</l>
               <l>Aryſe my Papiſtes, and defend the Pope your Preeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aryſe vp <hi>Dunce</hi> and <hi>Dorbell,</hi> and ſtande to your Sacrament,</l>
               <l>And ſpare for no Logicke, theyr natures to alienate:</l>
               <l>Of Breade into Fleſh, I thinke it conuenient,</l>
               <l>And Wine into Blood, quicke for to tranſlate:</l>
               <l>I might be more ſiner, with tranſubſtanciate.</l>
               <l>But ye knowe my meaning, my owne ſweete Boyes,</l>
               <l>I ſpeake to you Papiſtes, to reuiue my ioyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ <hi>Peter Lombardus,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquyne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eckius</hi> and <hi>Anſelm,</hi> Prelates of ſome truſt:</l>
               <l>Aryſe I ſay quickly, with your doctrine Serpentine,</l>
               <l>And fyll me the worlde, with your ranke Rebell ruſt:</l>
               <l>Your Bookes dooth remaine, though your bodyes be duſt.</l>
               <l>Whereby that ſome ſéede, in this time may growe,</l>
               <l>To the prayſe of your father, which full well ye doo knowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Aryſe vp <hi>Hyldebrand,</hi> for nowe it is hye tyme,</l>
               <l>To poyſon the world, by one meane or other:</l>
               <l>Thruſt in all helpes, ſlaunder, lye, and cryme,</l>
               <l>Playe as <hi>Alphoncius,</hi> played vy his owne Brother:</l>
               <l>Stryke out theyr braines be it Father or Mother,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Cayne</hi> dyd <hi>Abell,</hi> and I wyll you reward,</l>
               <l>With wylde fire and Brimſtone, or elſe it ſhall goe hard.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Aryſe vp <hi>Becker,</hi> Traytor to thy King,</l>
               <l>Sweate, ſweare and ſwell, againſt all thoſe procéedinges:</l>
               <l>That fayth, lyght or riſe, by any meanes bring.</l>
               <l>Reſiſt it betymes, and I will furder your ſpéedinges:</l>
               <l>And what I can doo, to hinder theyr féedinges,</l>
               <l>Aſſure your ſelues, as Sathan is my name,</l>
               <l>An aduerſary I am, and will perfourme the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Aryſe vp <hi>Dun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>, Wolſton,</hi> and <hi>Gooderick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aryſe vp all ye Scorpious of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aryſe vp <hi>Benedick, Frauncis,</hi> and <hi>Domynick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aryſe vp all the Papiſticall ſome:</l>
               <l>Out with your Portiſes, and defend my kingdome?</l>
               <l>Your Grayelles, and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yueners, Legendare and all,</l>
               <l>Croſſe, Cope, and Candleſstick, is elſe lyke to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Beſwinge them with holy Water, &amp; ring out your Bels,</l>
               <l>Blinde them with Pardons, diſple downe theyr ſinnes:</l>
               <l>Bleare them with Idols, and many thinges els,</l>
               <l>As Dirge, Mattens, and Maſſe, for ſcabbes and ſore ſhinnes:</l>
               <l>Some of <hi>Requiem</hi> ſome of <hi>Scala cali,</hi> not worth two pinnes,</l>
               <l>Yet out with them, though I am driuen to that néede,</l>
               <l>That all will be to lytle, nowe to doo the déede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Stand to it <hi>Stapleton, Dorman</hi> and <hi>Harding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Raſtall</hi> that rakehell, to mainteyne my order:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gardener,</hi> are worth the regarding,</l>
               <l>For kéeping my Articles, ſo long in this border:</l>
               <l>Do <hi>Story, Story,</hi> thou art worthy of Recorder,</l>
               <l>Thou ſtoodſt to it ſtoutly, againſt God and King.</l>
               <l>And at Tiborne deſperatly, gaue me an offering.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Frier <hi>Forreſt,</hi> and all his mery mates,</l>
               <l>Dyd yéeld me the like, with heart and good will:</l>
               <l>They puld of their Cowles, and hangd all ſaue the pates,</l>
               <l>In the honour of me, and thought it not yll:</l>
               <l>And Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> likewiſe at Tower hyll,</l>
               <l>Loſt there his head, for denying the King,</l>
               <l>To do ſupreame head, and for no other thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ What ſhould I ſpeake, what feates haue bene wrought,</l>
               <l>By Hypocrites and Papiſtes, my Children naturall:</l>
               <l>What Rebellion and ſedicion, by them hath bene ſought,</l>
               <l>Againſt King and Realme, it is knowen in generall:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lincolneshyre,</hi> and <hi>Yorkshyre,</hi> were firſt the originall,</l>
               <l>And then came the Weſt partes, with courage luſtily,</l>
               <l>To defend the Maſſe, and the groundes of Papiſtry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But nowe alas, their cloyning is ſo ſpide,</l>
               <l>That no way but flye, quite ouer the Sea:</l>
               <l>In <hi>England</hi> but a fewe, in reſpect I can hide:</l>
               <l>The Goſpell ſo be wrayes their obſcured knauerie.</l>
               <l>But yet ſome doe ſcape, by the meane of Hypocriſie,</l>
               <l>And beares it out braglie, and little will ſay,</l>
               <l>For fewe woordes is beſt, they hope for a day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And thoſe that are fled, out of Countreyes foyle,</l>
               <l>Haue friendſhippe priuelie to their contentation,</l>
               <l>And watche for the vauntage, to come to ſome ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>Gréeting by Letters, their whole generation,</l>
               <l>By ſubtill cyphering, is their demonſtration,</l>
               <l>Alluring the reſt, to ſtand to their hope,</l>
               <l>That the day is comming to haue againe their Pope.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Well, I will helpe, and reaſon to you knowe,</l>
               <l>To plant in theſe plaintiues, with all that I can:</l>
               <l>With all deuiſe poſſible, to ſeeke to ouerthrowe,</l>
               <l>All true obedience, and fidelitie from man:</l>
               <l>Therefore marke what I ſay, and marke what I ſcan,</l>
               <l>By Hypocriſte and pollycie, as I ſayd before,</l>
               <l>I will augment my kingdome, twiſe as much more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ One thouſand yéeres, in captiuitie I was,</l>
               <l>And ſo reſtrayned from my libertie and will:</l>
               <l>That nothing to my purpoſe, I could bring to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Which nowe makes me hungrie, to worke double yll:</l>
               <l>Reſpecting no perſon, but all I would kill,</l>
               <l>By all deuiſe poſſible, to infect them with euill,</l>
               <l>Loe, this is my practiſe, being Sathan the deuill.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Wherefore my owne Boyes, ye Papiſts in generall,</l>
               <l>Maſculine and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Feminine, of eyther kinde and gender:</l>
               <l>Woorke for your Father, and his kingdome infernall,</l>
               <l>That double torments, for your paines I may render:</l>
               <l>Blaſe out my benefites, that they be not ſlender,</l>
               <l>Kingdomes I can giue, beauty and renowne.</l>
               <l>To as many as before me, will ſtoope and fall downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Regard not theſe Preachers, but ſclaunder them as thus,</l>
               <l>That they be but men, and preach for lucres ſake:</l>
               <l>Againe, howe they are prowde, and too too couetous,</l>
               <l>Vicious, laſciuious, and can both marre and make:</l>
               <l>Praters and lyers, which nothing doe but crak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And howe that their Wiues are like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>their degre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Lyke Curtizans of <hi>Venice,</hi> for ought that all men ſées.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Their Children are by Lawe, called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llegitymats,</l>
               <l>Holde in that Lawe to proue their Mariage vile:</l>
               <l>And ſeeke by all meanes, their doinges to contaminate.</l>
               <l>To bring in contempt, and Gods v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> to exile:</l>
               <l>Be craftie my B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>s, theſe Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>t to beguile.</l>
               <l>Be Vſurers among them, and doe what ye can,</l>
               <l>Againſt right and reaſon, to hurt euerie man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I charge my faire Papiſts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and birth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>That hath Vicaridge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ds to beſtow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>To giue it thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which knowes not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Nor yet can diſcerne the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the Crowe</l>
               <l>They are Curates good inough, they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd but for a ſhowe,</l>
               <l>To mumble out the matter, of that which comes next,</l>
               <l>Making men beleeue, that their lyes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Then let the learned ſort, of the Papiſtes &amp; doe uſe ane,</l>
               <l>Powder ſo their Phraſes, with reaſons ſophiſticall:</l>
               <l>Alledging auncient cuſtome, and what tofore hath bene,</l>
               <l>From Fathers vnto Fathers, and Biſhops pontificall:</l>
               <l>From Councell to Councell, and lawes Canonycall,</l>
               <l>To ſay it muſt be thus, and that ſtandes with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Though Scripture to the contrary, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that to drawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And euer kéepe in corners, a Pſalter of Saint <hi>Mary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Challice and a Pare, for Maſſe if néede require:</l>
               <l>A Crewſible and a Stone, called <hi>Superaltary,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Ship for your Franckencenſe, and a Pan for your Fire:</l>
               <l>A Saints bell beſide, to ring all in the Quire,</l>
               <l>That when the bleſſed Hoſt, ſhall come ouer his head,</l>
               <l>The verie body of Chriſte, a lye in forme of bread.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ As for Veſtments and Coapes, excuſe them by pretence,</l>
               <l>That Cuſhins and Curtens, of them ye will make:</l>
               <l>If ye chaunce to be ſpied, ye ſée that the offence,</l>
               <l>Is but a hundred Markes, for our God in a Cake:</l>
               <l>Ye ſhalbe borne withall beſide, for your fréendes ſake,</l>
               <l>The penaltie is not great, I thinke it not too mych,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that I doe knowe, my Papiſtes are too rych.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Externlie be couetous, and cappe to euery Dogge.</l>
               <l>Giue openlie to the poore, that all the world may ſée:</l>
               <l>In ſecrets be as gentle, as any rauening Hogge,</l>
               <l>And for loue giue nothing, but all for vaine glorie:</l>
               <l>Exclude the Scriptures, and byd them reade the ſtorie</l>
               <l>Of Robin hood, and Guye, which was both tall and ſtout,</l>
               <l>And Beuis of Southampton, to ſéeke the matter out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ With theſe and ſuch lyke, perſwade them day by day,</l>
               <l>To reade and learne, yea perfectly by hart:</l>
               <l>The Scriptures will but bréede, great hereſies, ſo ſay,</l>
               <l>And make them to diſpayre, in ſearching euery part:</l>
               <l>Byd them followe their vocation, and that is Plough &amp; Cart,</l>
               <l>For Tinckers and Coblers, it is nothing conuenient,</l>
               <l>To deſire to know the waight of Gods commaundement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Make their burthens heauie, and yours to be but lyght,</l>
               <l>As the Pharaſies dyd, to whome was cried woe:</l>
               <l>And more then this, ye muſt call the blacke all whight,</l>
               <l>And the whyte the blacke, with other lyings moe:</l>
               <l>And how that ſprites doe walke, if one doe crye but boe,</l>
               <l>And that Soules in purgatorie, for pardon ſtill doe crye,</l>
               <l>For a thouſand dayes and od, and ſay it is no lye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For other kinde of Ceremonies, that holy is to name,</l>
               <l>As holy Water, holy Bread, holy Fire, holy Oyle:</l>
               <l>Holy Beades holy Candle, holy Smoke, holy Flame,</l>
               <l>Holy Ground, holy Church, holy Sanctuary ſoyle:</l>
               <l>Holy Bels, holy Banners, holy Horſe, holy Moyle,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the common people to induſe.</l>
               <l>By the reaſon that long time, hath brought them out of vſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But if the world chaunge, as you looke that it ſhould,</l>
               <l>And as my Magicians, by Arte ſo dooth hope,</l>
               <l>Aſſure your ſelues Villaines, and thereof be bold,</l>
               <l>Theſe Ceremonies ſhall vp, by the power of the Pope:</l>
               <l>Yea, and the Sacrament too, ſhalbe hangd in a Rope,</l>
               <l>Ouer the hye Alter, as it was wont to bée,</l>
               <l>And honored as God, both with cap and knée.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Munkes, Nunnes and Friers, black, white, and graie,</l>
               <l>Chanons, Anckres, and Anckreſſes, all ſhall vp againe:</l>
               <l>Pilgrimages, and Chappels, ſtanding by the hie waie,</l>
               <l>Croſſes, ſingle and double, for Saint <hi>Iones</hi> to be plaine:</l>
               <l>Gang dayes, and Proceſſion, with other trifles vaine,</l>
               <l>Diſpling and Confeſſion, for our ſtunes in Lent,</l>
               <l>All muſt vp againe, my Papiſtes hath ſo ment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Practiſe, prate and Coniure, plaie <hi>Silueſters</hi> part,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Hildebrand</hi> that hell hound moſt execrable:</l>
               <l>Poiſon Prince, or King, and conſume them by Arte,</l>
               <l>As diuers haue bene ſtirred, by the Romiſh rable:</l>
               <l>Flatter, lye, and cogge, at euerie mans Table,</l>
               <l>Hauing blinde Prophecies, and whiſper in their eare,</l>
               <l>That ere long we ſhall haue, great chaunge of this geare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Hang together lyke burres, againſt theſe prating Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</l>
               <l>Charge them to liue ill, and out of all good order:</l>
               <l>Terme them bréeders of ſects, and painted Preſſcians,</l>
               <l>And howe they Preache for money, in euerie border:</l>
               <l>Séeke Scriptures againſt them, and many a falſe Recorder,</l>
               <l>Béelie them in corners, yet flatter to their face,</l>
               <l>Till iuſt time ſhall ſerue, their ſtate to diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Your nature of it ſelfe, hath practiſes vnſpeakable,</l>
               <l>As occaſion ſerueth, ſo proſecute your mindes:</l>
               <l>And I your olde Father, wyll be to you as fauourable,</l>
               <l>And worke by all meanes, to furder your kindes:</l>
               <l>Séeme Angels of lyght, which all the world blindes,</l>
               <l>But be verie Woolues, if néede doe ſo require,</l>
               <l>That once againe in time, we may haue our deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Perſecute theſe Proteſtants, as long as ye haue breath,</l>
               <l>Ye ſée in ſecuritie, they lull them ſelues a ſléepe:</l>
               <l>Fraught with all ydleneſſe, and great feares of death,</l>
               <l>Tymerous and weake, faynt hearted lyke Shéepe,</l>
               <l>Breakers of promiſe, no touch they wyll kéepe,</l>
               <l>The Papiſt is more conſtant, for all their proteſtation,</l>
               <l>And ſo giue it out, to euerie Congregation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Theſe and ſuch ſclaunders, on them ye muſt rayſe.</l>
               <l>As carnall cauyllers, to maynteyne their affection:</l>
               <l>Lyke flatterers and diſſemblers, in theſe latter dayes,</l>
               <l>Not ſéeing their ſelues, but all others correction:</l>
               <l>Proude puffed Prelates, which ſtandes vpon election,</l>
               <l>Preciſe Hypocrites, rebukers of others workes,</l>
               <l>When ſecretly them ſelues, are worſe then any Turkes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Thus ye muſt handle, your cloynings by clouting,</l>
               <l>And whiſper in corners, this world wyll not laſt:</l>
               <l>In euerie honeſt thing, make you a doubting,</l>
               <l>To turne all good meanings, as a iugling caſt:</l>
               <l>That thing that's to come, ſay you it is paſt.</l>
               <l>As the Reſurrection, the chéefe hope and ioy:</l>
               <l>Like Saduces and Epicures, ſéeke you it to annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ I ſpeake to you Papiſts, which are of ſome calling,</l>
               <l>Setled in ſecurity, no Lawe to detect you:</l>
               <l>Face out theſe Proteſtants, with facing and bralling,</l>
               <l>Calling them beggers, and why ſhould they correct you:</l>
               <l>Ye haue Statute againſt them, if they once ſuſpect you.</l>
               <l>Or call you Papiſts, eyther though Papiſts ye be:</l>
               <l>Suffer no ſuch crime, againſt your Hypocriſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Other meanes there is, and marke my practiſe well,</l>
               <l>Linke with them in Mariage, much for honors ſake:</l>
               <l>Your So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes with their Daughters, for a thing that I ſmell,</l>
               <l>Your Daughters with their Sonnes, iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ioynter to take:</l>
               <l>This coniunction copulatiue, I my ſelfe will make,</l>
               <l>Knowing that the Woman, within a yeere or twaine,</l>
               <l>Will turne my new Goſpeller, to olde cuſtome againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ As <hi>Iezabell</hi> did <hi>Achab,</hi> oh my owne Deuile,</l>
               <l>As the <hi>Amonites</hi> and <hi>Edomytes,</hi> cauſed the wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To commit Idolatrie, and the hie God to deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>So let your Daughters be the lyke patron:</l>
               <l>And to make them deleeue, there is no God to Mammon,</l>
               <l>Drawing their mindes; both at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed and at bord,</l>
               <l>Cleane from the trueth, and to deny the Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Alſo I charge you, to ſuccor helpe and inde;</l>
               <l>All obſcure Papiſtes, yea, Traytors in effect:</l>
               <l>Blinde Chaplaines in your hyntes, you néede not be afraide,</l>
               <l>The Lawes hath that charitie, that none ſhall you correct.</l>
               <l>Let Scholemaiſters likewiſe all yonglings infect,</l>
               <l>And kéepe them in their houſe, your Familie to teach,</l>
               <l>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare, and mocke, thoſe that trueth doe preach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And within your lyberties, if any tyrant dwell,</l>
               <l>That praties of the Teſtament, eyther olde or new:</l>
               <l>Remoue me that fellowe, and ſay he is a rebell,</l>
               <l>A Iacke, a buſie body, of the little flocke or crew:</l>
               <l>Ioyne ſo your friendſhip, whatſoeuer then enſew,</l>
               <l>That twenty for one, may then be on your ſide,</l>
               <l>Your knaueries to mainteine, and your treaſons to hide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And then your abilities, your credife ſhall aduaunce,</l>
               <l>Your friendſhip by Mariage, ſhall complaint qualifie:</l>
               <l>That in twenty miles compaſſe, without it be a chaunce,</l>
               <l>None ſhall dare ſay, once againſt your Papiſtrie:</l>
               <l>Marrie ſome will thinke that you are Apoſtaſie,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in times paſt, ye were great profeſſors,</l>
               <l>And nowe are become, euen my owne ſucceſſors.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And I will about to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſtyrre vp your Pope, great part for to take:</l>
               <l>With Gallies, with Men, to helpe to mainteine,</l>
               <l>His friendes in all partes, for me the Diuels ſake:</l>
               <l>In euerie Princes Court, ſome ſpies I will make,</l>
               <l>To ſée and not ſée, till time ſhalbe méete,</l>
               <l>Then Letters within Letters, ſhall trot about the ſtréete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Bulles, curſes, and Pardons, in cornors ſhalbe loſt,</l>
               <l>And Images of waxe, in dunghyls ſhalbe found:</l>
               <l>Coniuring to conſume, the beſt in euery coſt,</l>
               <l>To fruſtrats the trueth, and vice for to abound:</l>
               <l>And eke the profeſſors, to haue them hangd or drownd,</l>
               <l>This is my intent, and to this I ſet my hand,</l>
               <l>Lyke a Diuell incarnate, to poiſon euery Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And ſpecially this <hi>England,</hi> which cléerely hath exilde,</l>
               <l>The Pope my owne Boy, and all his ſupreme power:</l>
               <l>As Monkes, Nuns, and Friers, whoſe lying hath beguilde,</l>
               <l>Euery Chriſtian Realme, time day and hower:</l>
               <l>Altering all ſwéete thinges, to intollerable ſower,</l>
               <l>Theſe I ſay are voyde, which now makes me ſo mad,</l>
               <l>That thouſandes I will reuenge, if it be to be had.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Reſpecting no man, for this ye doe knowe,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Chriſt</hi> I aſſaulted, and little could preuaile:</l>
               <l>He was too ſtrong for me, when it came to the ſhows,</l>
               <l>His power was ſo great, I began for to quaile:</l>
               <l>He had me anoide, and I turnd my taile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But as for the reſt, that nowe are here behinde,</l>
               <l>Are leſſe in the ſpirite, and more ſhall knowe my minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For I ſée that all men, giuen to ſelf loue,</l>
               <l>And affection ſo rules, nowo in euerie condition:</l>
               <l>That eaſely I may enter, and my practiſe proue,</l>
               <l>In euery Eſtate, without feare or Commiſſion:</l>
               <l>And moſt I knowe by text are children of perdicion,</l>
               <l>Then haue among my owne, giuen me by prouidence,</l>
               <l>Reproued by God, for their beaſtly inſolence.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Hardened is their hearts, more obſtinate then <hi>Pharao,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That they cannot repent, ſo ſtony is their hearts:</l>
               <l>As trayterous as <hi>Iudas,</hi> as tyrannous as <hi>Nero,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As letcherous as Goates, more vile in all partes:</l>
               <l>Babylonicall Hoores, mates for all Martes,</l>
               <l>Lyers, flatterers, defilers of Virginitie,</l>
               <l>Breakers of wedlocke, deteſters of Diuinitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Fraught with vaine glorie, farre beyond meaſure,</l>
               <l>Pufte vp with pride, exceſſiue in Apparell:</l>
               <l>Couetous as Diuels, inſaciate in Treaſure:</l>
               <l>As malicious as Mahound, more ready to quarrell,</l>
               <l>As dronken as <hi>Bacchus,</hi> ſitting on a Barrell:</l>
               <l>As poiſon as Adders, as gentle as curre Dogges,</l>
               <l>As filthy as carion, as rausnous as Hogges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Theſe are one ſort of the Babylonicall kinde,</l>
               <l>An other more finer, their praie to allure:</l>
               <l>Adulate créepers, in corners farre behinde,</l>
               <l>Soothing thoſe thinges, which is lykeſt to endare:</l>
               <l>Well ſéene in Palmeſtrie, and in Phiſicke ſure,</l>
               <l>To whiſper with the Feminine, of <hi>Venus</hi> and her ginnes,</l>
               <l>Prouing their complexion, not for their Huſbands ſkinnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ In the blinde world, as the Heretikes doe it call,</l>
               <l>Then tooke I moſt eaſe, my miſchéefes to prefarre:</l>
               <l>The Popes Traditions, by force of Lawes canonicall,</l>
               <l>Did alwayes fight for me, all godlineſſe to marre:</l>
               <l>I let them burne and hang, and ſéeke them where they ware,</l>
               <l>While I lay at mine eaſe, in hell with flaming fiers,</l>
               <l>With Popes, Biſhops, &amp; Munks, with fat growe head Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And of euerie ſort ſome, I néede not them to name,</l>
               <l>Of both kindes and genders, of hye and lowe degrée:</l>
               <l>Many a mynſing Nunne, and many a noble Dame,</l>
               <l>In hell is nowe reſident, which dines and ſuppes with me:</l>
               <l>As <hi>Semiramis</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> which liued all in glorie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flora</hi> and <hi>Lais,</hi> gyrles of ſuch report,</l>
               <l>That ſince their time, the proudeſt may come ſhort.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Nemroth,</hi> buylding ſo hie,</l>
               <l>That God he moude to wrath, by his great ambition:</l>
               <l>A Towre for to reare: he meant to touch the Skie,</l>
               <l>The wonder of the world, a large and great commiſſion:</l>
               <l>What ſhould I ſpeake of <hi>Pharao,</hi> the lyke proued condition,</l>
               <l>Which through the red Seas, his power ſo would leade,</l>
               <l>In the ſpight of God, which all dooth excende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ <hi>Holophernes</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> had like aſpiring mindes,</l>
               <l>And diuers other, which in Stories I haue read:</l>
               <l>The Diuell is not ignoraunt, of his owne proper kindes,</l>
               <l>Which God threwe downe, and made their doings dead:</l>
               <l>Innumerable there haue bene, as afore I ſayd,</l>
               <l>Which in working miſchiefe, in this world did excell,</l>
               <l>That nowe take reward, with me the Diuell of hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Wherefore my owne Boyes my councell nowe obſerue,</l>
               <l>And my practiſes alſo put in execution:</l>
               <l>And rich I can make you, if that your turne will ſerue,</l>
               <l>By giuing you lybertie, by my inſtitution:</l>
               <l>To oppreſſe, to extort, without reſtitution,</l>
               <l>To powle, pill, and pinch, by force power and might,</l>
               <l>By hooke, crooke, and councell, be doing day and night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Let all thinges be common, goods, mayde, and wife,</l>
               <l>Take time while time is, there is no reſurrection:</l>
               <l>Be not beaſtly cowards, but ſtyrre vp all ſtrife,</l>
               <l>To Princes and Rulers, be in no ſubiection:</l>
               <l>A figge for the Lawes, paſſe for no correction,</l>
               <l>Styrre vp ſedition, rebellion and filthy lyes,</l>
               <l>And ſweare it out lyke tyraunts, for God he hath no eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Search about for ſectes, of all ſorts and kindes,</l>
               <l>Mainteyne your affections, make Scriptures but a cloke:</l>
               <l>Let that be your Religion, that beſt pleaſe your mindes,</l>
               <l>Stand vpon ſelfe will, and by craft ſéeke to choke</l>
               <l>Simple honeſt men; if argument they prouoke,</l>
               <l>And ſay they haue no ſkill, trueth to vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>But if they will receyue, let them takte at your hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Looſe no kinde of credite, in your ſpirituall function,</l>
               <l>Say that you be called, as plainly dooth appeare:</l>
               <l>Binde the people whole to ſome olde Iniunction,</l>
               <l>That hath not bene in print, this forty, or fifty yeare:</l>
               <l>Tell them you are Lordes, ouer Towne and Sheare,</l>
               <l>Striue with them for tythes, to kéepe them in good awe,</l>
               <l>To kéepe their heads occupied, in following of your Lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And then may you the whyles, preach and teach your fill,</l>
               <l>And call them raſcall rebelles, which no order will kéepe:</l>
               <l>Forbid them Communion, ſéeke their ſoules to kill,</l>
               <l>Lyke a raging Woolfe among the ſimple Shéepe:</l>
               <l>And when the poore doth crie, be you faſt a ſléepe,</l>
               <l>Yet ſpeake you to the pariſh, their charitie to extend,</l>
               <l>But take you all &amp; giue nothing, to neyther foe nor fréend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And where you are conſtrained, to preach once a quarter,</l>
               <l>Or elſe to hyre one fowre times in the yéere:</l>
               <l>Preach me ſuch ſtuffe, as includes no great matter,</l>
               <l>As woorkes for to iuſtifie, when ſaith is nothing néere:</l>
               <l>All out of Apoerypha, let your woordes appeers,</l>
               <l>Or els by vaine fables, as <hi>Ouid</hi> or <hi>Horace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To beautifie your ſentence, lyke a glorious Aſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Medle not with Chriſt, nor with his holy Paſſion;</l>
               <l>Nor yet with faith, neyther ſay it is vnſearchable:</l>
               <l>Come not neere Election, nor Gods Predeſtination,</l>
               <l>It is no meate for Mowers, to be talk't at their table:</l>
               <l>And howe the new Teſtament, is all inſcrutable.</l>
               <l>Put them in a feare to driue them from the loue,</l>
               <l>For running into errors, your argument to proue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And ſome of you be gentle, and ſubtill as the Foxe,</l>
               <l>Holde in with the rycheſt, and ducke at euery word:</l>
               <l>That if the time ſhould chaunge, and God againe in boxe,</l>
               <l>Ye were an honeſt man, and thereof take record:</l>
               <l>Play on both handes, for that will beſt accord,</l>
               <l>To preuent the times, howſoeuer they fall out,</l>
               <l>And you to haue the place, of that you goe about.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Marry not in any wiſe, for that is greateſt charge.</l>
               <l>But borrowe of your neyghbours, as I will you aſſigne:</l>
               <l>And againſt thoſe that doe marry, ſpeake ſomewhat large,</l>
               <l>Their chyldren to be baſtardes, and bréede vnlawfull lyne:</l>
               <l>Their Wiues to be Peacockes, or Miſtreſſe new diuine,</l>
               <l>Theſe termes ye muſt haue, Vertue to diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Whyle you lyke vſurpers, may créepe into their place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Suffer all ſclaunder, againſt God and his trueth,</l>
               <l>And prayſe the olde faſhion, in king <hi>Arthurs</hi> dayes:</l>
               <l>Of Abbaies, of Monaſteries, howe it is great rueth,</l>
               <l>To haue them pluckt downe, and ſo the eldeſt ſayes:</l>
               <l>And howe it was merrie, when Robin hoods playes,</l>
               <l>Was in euerie Towne, the Morrice and the foole,</l>
               <l>The May poll, &amp; the Drum, to bring the Calfe from ſchoole.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ With <hi>Megge, Madge,</hi> and <hi>Marian,</hi> about the poll to daunce,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Stephen</hi> that tall ſtripling, to leade Volans dale:</l>
               <l>With roging Gangwéeke, a goodly remembraunce,</l>
               <l>With Banners all a flaunt, with Cakes, Chéeſe, and Ale:</l>
               <l>With beades in euery hand, our Prayers ſtoode by tale,</l>
               <l>This was a merie world, talke among your meany,</l>
               <l>And then of good Egges, ye might haue twenty for a penny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ With this and ſuch paultrie, when ye ſée time and place,</l>
               <l>And the people apte, this way to be fead:</l>
               <l>Step in for a vauntage, and exclude Gods grace,</l>
               <l>Let the blinde leade the blinde, this text I haue read:</l>
               <l>For in kéeping them blinde, without cléere diſcerning,</l>
               <l>Ye make them ſubiect, and reſerue your owne learning,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Ye ſée and you knowe, that all is not cleare,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that ſome profite on them doth depend:</l>
               <l>As Aduent, Lent, and rynging all the whole yeare,</l>
               <l>Organs and ſinging, I knowe not to what end:</l>
               <l>Images in Glaſſe windowes, and none will it amend,</l>
               <l>Criſome cloath and offeringes, ſtill they doe ſtand,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they bring profite, my Boyes to this Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Biſhoprickes and Benefices, my owne Childe the Pope.</l>
               <l>Enlarged vnto thouſands, and ſtill they doe ſtand:</l>
               <l>And made them Lord Biſhops, becauſe they ſhould not ſlope,</l>
               <l>Where Chriſte had no ſea, nor money in his hand:</l>
               <l>When <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould haue cuſtome, in Scripture it is ſcand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> went a fiſhing, money in fiſhe to finde,</l>
               <l>To pay the full duetie, as Chriſt had him aſſignde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But goe you a fleaſhing, ye haue no ſuch power,</l>
               <l>But yet gather money, for that will helpe at néede:</l>
               <l>Ye ſee and ye knowe, at this preſent hower,</l>
               <l>That all the packes of Prelates are couetous in déede:</l>
               <l>For ſome of them I knowe, ſo much in wealth excéede.</l>
               <l>That Vſurers they be, and yet doe ſerue the cure,</l>
               <l>Theſe be olde Boyes, to make their liuing ſure,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Corne maſters beſide, and learne to buie and ſell,</l>
               <l>Thus ye muſt blaſe them, and perchaunce ſay true:</l>
               <l>But whether it be or no, I the Diuell of hell,</l>
               <l>Doe teach you to practiſe, their names to ſubdue:</l>
               <l>Be buſie among them, both with olde and new,</l>
               <l>And you ſhall haue my bleſſing, for all your lewd workes,</l>
               <l>Among all Reprobates, Infidels and <hi>Turkes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Out vpon <hi>Luther, Wyckleſe,</hi> and <hi>Zwynglius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For they wrought my ſpoyle, by their predycation:</l>
               <l>Out vpon <hi>Caluyne,</hi> and <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Out vpon <hi>Tyndale,</hi> and all his generation:</l>
               <l>Out vpon <hi>Bale</hi> for by his demonſtration,</l>
               <l>The whole Realme of <hi>England,</hi> receyued ſuch light,</l>
               <l>That world without ende, I beare them all ſpight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Ye out of all Proteſtants, all Papiſts nowe crie,</l>
               <l>And ſpecially thoſe that ſet out large Bookes:</l>
               <l>As the Byble and Teſtament, or the holy Euangelie,</l>
               <l>A pockes lyght vpon them, that on them oft lookes:</l>
               <l>They haue caught my ſonne, the Pope in ſuch hookes,</l>
               <l>That in <hi>England</hi> nowe he is little regarded,</l>
               <l>But as by Antichriſt, is often rewarded.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ <hi>Bale</hi> with his Pageant of Popes, hath ſet them ſo out.</l>
               <l>Their whole liues and trades, and all their conditions:</l>
               <l>The Image of Iniquitie, hath rypt euery dout.</l>
               <l>That the Pope is known, the father of Superſtitions:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caluy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</hi> againe, with his Booke of Inſtitutions,</l>
               <l>Hath ſo vnabled the Popes cannon lawes,</l>
               <l>That all that is Romiſh, is not woorth two ſtrawes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea and diuers others, againſt him haue written,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Foxe</hi> in his Booke, that Monuments he calles:</l>
               <l>Which the Popes guttes out of his belly hath bitten,</l>
               <l>By arguments ſtrong, hath throwne the Popes bralles:</l>
               <l>But by fire and faggot, I ſought all their falles,</l>
               <l>And will doo ſtill, my malice to ſatiſfie,</l>
               <l>Againſt theſe Heretikes, which doe vexe me daylie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Farewell my Babes, and newe borne Apoſtates,</l>
               <l>Farewell my Papiſtes, and whoremonger villaines:</l>
               <l>Farewell all Epicures, and all dronken balde pates,</l>
               <l>Farewell my Chaplaines, moſt filthy fountaines:</l>
               <l>Farewell my diſſembling knaues, that heaps like mountains</l>
               <l>Farewell my Hypocrites, fraught with adulation,</l>
               <l>For I muſt to hell, to prepare your damnation.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Laurence Ramſey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:10"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London for <hi>Tymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Rider, and are to be ſolde at the</hi> lyttle North doore of Paules Church, at the ſigne of the blacke Boy, by Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Kyrkham.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20445:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
